Individually catalogued manuscripts, 1591-2005 Various call numbers
Lilly Library
- Anonymous cryptographic manuscript, ca. 1780, 1867
  Unique and unpublished late 18th century (ca. 1780 per dealer's description) cryptographic manuscript, with 15 handwritten pages of undeciphered code in the form of fractions, numerals and slash-marks. The manuscript's initial lines of code, which are shorter and centered on the page, suggest a title or attribution; these are followed by nearly 200 lines of encrypted text, which is divided into sections with alphabetical headings. The encrypted pages are for the most part interleaved with blanks, suggesting that the author may have intended the encrypted text to be decoded. Also included at the back of the volume are two additional, unrelated encrypted texts, both of which are signed and dated to the 19th century. The first is a lengthy series of mathematical exercises (143 p.) involving fractions signed, "Christophorus Althaus Münster 1817"; and the second a transcription of five German poems (7 p.), entitled, "Carmina diversa ex optimis poetis exce[r]pta" and dated 1867. Includes numerous blank leaves as well.
- Geometrisches Sinnspiel, [between 1891 and 1923]
  2012.0
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12429950
  Consists of a manuscript book of tangram puzzle solutions, written by a school teacher from Bartholfelde as a gift for Ernst August, Crown Prince of Hanover. The text is in German cursive, known as Kurrent or Alte Deutsche Schrift. Thirty-one leaves of the volume have handwritten text and tangram puzzle solutions. The solutions have short descriptions of the solutions accompanying them.
- Licensed Victuallers' Protection Society of London album, 1875-1877
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767874
  An album presented to W. J. Wetenhall, the outgoing Chairman of the Licensed Victuallers' Protection Society of London, by H. R. Sharman, the Society's secretary. The album covers the activities of the Society for 1876, the year Wetenhall was Chairman of the Society. After the initial introductory material about Wetenhall, including a brief biography and portrait, and the Society, the album has six groupings of material: Home Counties League; Excursion; Parliamentary Reports, Acts, Papers, & Letters; Anniversary Dinner; Testimonial; and Miscellaneous, Including False Character Cases, Funeral of Col. Richards, Committee Dinners, Grocers Licenses, National League Conference, Letters, &c. It concludes with a description of the Transfer of the Keys ceremony in which Wetenhall stepped down and the new Chairman, Alfred A. Cole, was inaugurated. Materials in the album include society publications and programs, newspaper clippings, manuscript correspondence and notes, memoranda, Parliamentary publications, and telegraphs.
- Spanish document of land sale, ca. 1618
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8248452
  17th century Spanish language holograph land sale document involving a vineyard in the pueblo de Calellia de Palafrugell, near Gerona, Spain.
- Indiana bank notes and emphemera, 1815-2004
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8626994
  Collection consists of forty Indiana bank notes from 1815-1859 (several are in uncut sheets of 2-3 notes), one facsimile $20.00 bill (The Marine Bank of Buffalo 1902), a facsimile page from a Citizens' Bank of Gosport checkbook, a proof copy for a "2009 Indiana Currency Calendar," a printout of an article, "Free banking in Gosport," by Douglass Boshkoff (originally published in The Ten O'Clock News, Mar. 2004), and three color photographs (ca. 2000; two photos taken in Shoals, Ind. ("Dover Hill") and a photo of the "Welcome to Historic Gosport" sign).
- Fire insurance policy and premium receipts, 1809-1821
  Gift: 2004
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11653032
  Fire insurance policy taken out by Isaac Strutt, Esq., of Groton (1809) and receipts for premiums paid (1810-1821). Strutt took out a policy for £2200 that insured ten buildings: a mansion house, a farm house, a cart lodge, two brewhouse and dairy buildings, and five stables and barns. Strutt paid £6 and 1 shilling annually for coverage.
- Registro de escrituras publicas Puebla, March-April 1594
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8627017
  A bound collection of notarized documents from the notary public Juan de la Parra Diosdado, written in Puebla de los Angeles (Mexico) in 1594. The documents include powers of attorney, contracts of sale and purchase, marriage dowries, wills, and promissory notes. The file reflects the legal dealings of the period in the second city of New Spain.
- Aaron Copland's script for Orson Welles' The Five Kings, 1939-1991
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8264417
  The original typed script ([129] leaves for the play, The five kings, includes Copland's extensive handwritten notes, drawings and a half sheet of music. The script is accompanied by four original photographs; in addition, there are 9 leaves of colored xerox reproductions of 15 photographs, a black & white inscribed photograph (dated 1985) of Copland, an invitation to a memorial concert for Copland (Apr. 20, 1991), a handwritten note to Victor [Busso] from Verna Fine (Apr. 22, 1991), and the program for the Aaron Copland Memorial Concert (Apr. 20, 1991). Photographs include two black and white portraits of Copland (ca. 1957), various pictures taken during the 1980s with Copland (featured in the pictures are Leonard Bernstein, Victor Hugo Busso, Irene Wiley and Elliot Goldenthal). From 1982 to 1987 Victor Busso acted a the primary caretaker for Copland, managing his household, cooking and keeping track of nurses. During that time, Busso took on several friends as cohelpers, among which were Irene Wiley and Elliott Goldenthal. For additional information, see Howard Pollack's Aaron Copland (Champaign, IL: University of Illinois Press, 2000), p. 543-544.
- On the banks of the Wabash, 24 Apr. 1903
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10981837
  Holograph copy of "On the banks of the Wabash, far away," signed by Paul Dresser and dated "4/24/1903."
- Pontus Carles, ca. 1991
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11653054
  Catalogue for Pontus Carles' 1991 exhibit at the Marc Espinosa gallery in Paris and Galerie F in Berlin. Accompanying manuscript note from Thomas Günther removed to Bibliographical File.
- Be Well - Dallas Henke, 2010
  2011.0
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11344554
  Two impressions of Be Well from the portfolio Without Witness (2010). Autograph letter from the artist to Breon Mitchell removed to vertical file, Dept. of Manuscripts.
- Collection of 115 drawings and watercolors, 1914-1918
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8080728
  A collection of 115 drawings and watercolors related to the home front in Dijon, France, during World War I. The illustrations provide a glimpse of daily life in Dijon, the latest fashions, regional clothing styles, and military life during the war; most of the illustrations are accompanied by holograph comments, observations and musings. There are several illustrations of American Red Cross nurses, with the notation, "Les Américaines à Dijon." Some of the notes appear to be addressed to the soldiers' families. The illustrations vary in size (12-32 cm.), many of which are rendered on slips and scraps of paper or are cut into various shapes, and are mounted on folded leaves of various colors of heavy paper (27 folded leaves). The collection also includes seven loose leaves of illustrations.
- Hanakichō, 1876
  Gift: 1996
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12346976
  Unique artists' book from the library of Ruth E. Adomeit. Accordion style, bound in embroidered-cloth boards.
- Family photo album with triptych fore-edge painting, 1860-1870
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8235582
  Includes 45 portraits (several of which are tintype or ferrotype) of the Hawkins family from the 19th century. Those photographs that are labeled include the names: Laura B. Hawkins, "Uncle" Merton J. Hawkins, Anne-Elizabeth Robinson ("Irene's mother"), "Aunt" Jane Jagger ("sister to mother"), Emily Turner, Anna Stenus (?), John Mitchell Stenus, Abram Homer (?) Stenus, Uncle Sirus(?) Stenus.
- Bohemian Nature Print album, ca. 1740-1810
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/10814420
  An amateur nature-print album of 135 large specimens of garden plants, field flowers and medicinal plants, printed in grey or grey-black ink on 28 folding plates and 104 folio leaves, all hand-colored by a contemporary hand (with the exception of two), manuscript nomenclature in Latin and Czech. Three of the largest impressions are of new world plants--tobacco, love-lies-bleeds, and staghorn sumac. The plates are printed in grey and are hand-colored to match the original plant; some are touched with varnish. The 100 terminal blank leaves were used to dry and flatten the specimens. Each plate is annotated in brown ink (a slightly larger hand has corrected or expanded these annotations in black ink). The inclusion of Czech and some German vernacular names points to the album's place of production.
- Two Georg Wilhelm Freytag autograph letters, 1829-1830
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767114
  Two letters by G. W. Freytag to an unknown senior civil servant, possibly Johannes Schulze in the Ministry of Culture in Berlin. The first letter is by G. W. Freytag to the recipient thanking him for a diploma of the Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften, which Freytag was admitted to on Dec. 10 1829. It also makes reference to a dictionary that his is working on. The second letter also concerns the dictionary, which is most likely his "Lexicon Arabico-Latinum," the first volume of which was published in 1830. Also, included in is an older biographical manuscript.
- Album of Aristophanes' "The Acharnians" at Leamington College, 1892
  Purchase: 2008
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8068048
  Contains correspondence, photographs, music, and other printed items relating to the production of Aristophanes' "The Acharnians" in 1892, inspired by the headmaster of Leamington College at the time, W. J. Ford. For this production Ford performed the role of Dicaeopolis and spoke a new parabasis, written by himself. The items are pasted onto 22 unnumbered leaves of the album and consist of 1) Autograph letter from Ford's widow, Kitty, to his brother Lionel Ford, 5 June 1922 presenting this volume. -- 2) Large handbill or poster for the production (28 x 21.5 cm), printed in red and black, advertising dates and times of the three performances on 15, 17, and 20 June. -- 3) Caricature frontispiece designed (according to Mrs.Ford's letter and a review pasted into the volume) by Henry Ford, fourth brother of W.J. Ford. -- 4) Printed programme (2 p., 24.5 x 18 cm.) for the play, detailing actors, scenery designer, composer, etc. -- 5. 8 large photographs (each approx. 15 x 20.8 cm.) of the action and set of the production; with a general view of the college, taken (according to a review which reproduces one of them) by Smart and son of Leamington. With captions in ink, presumably by W. J. Ford. -- 6) A large variety of press cuttings of review of the play, beginning with the school magazine ("The Leamingtonian") and continuing with local and national journals, including the Leamington News, the Birmingham Post, the Daily Graphic, Vanity Fair, the Cheltenham Chronicle and the St. James's Gazette, all identified in the same hand as item 5. -- 7. Text of the Parabasis written by W. J. Ford, in both Greek and English (facing pages), printed but cut out and mounted; with a note also in the same hand. -- 8. The Music to the Acharnians of Aristophanes. Composed for performance at Leamington College in 1892 by George Prior, Mus: D: Oxon. Small folio, 15 p., the title page printed in letterpress (on green card) and the main text of the music reproduced in photolithography(?).
- The Iliad of Homer, 1870
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8444557
  Title page printed in red and black. Lilly Library copy is extra-illustrated with six steel engraved portraits of Bryant, 40 reproductions of classical engravings by Carter and Andrews, and twelve and a half pages of Bryant's original holograph manuscript leaves bound into the text at appropriate intervals. Bound in contemporary red morocco, ruled in gilt on the covers and compartments on the spines, raised bands, gilt dentelles, blue cloth endpapers.
- Barter's Homer's Iliad notes, 1854
  Purchase: 2004
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8633532
  Barter's heavily corrected working manuscript for his lengthy and discursive notes to accompany his full translation of the Illiad, published by Longman in 1854. In 1850 Pickering published a collection of Poems, four printed pieces of which the author has pasted in with the manuscript note, "This printed matter is from my volume of poems published by Pickering in 1850. WGTB."
- Sketch for Zázrak v rodině - František Langer, 192-?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11344528
  Sketch for the cover of Zázrak v rodině: humoristický román (1929), here titled Zázrak v rodině: román.
- Noc s Ofélií fragment, 1973
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/14023926
  Manuscript, with corrections, of the text Noc s Ofélií, in the author's hand.
- Edward Rehatsek letter, 18 Jan. 1881
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767913
  Autographed letter, dated January 18, 1881 in Bombay (Mumbai), India, from Edward Rehatsek to Mr. Wood. Rehatsek reviews Mortimer Howell's A Grammar of the Classical Arabic Language. He concludes that it is a knowledgeable but impractical work since the advanced scholars who could best make use of it would go directly to the sources themselves. A more practical endeavor for Howell, who was in the employ of the government, would have been a descriptive catalogue of the Arabic and Persian manuscripts in the Northwest provinces, of which only those in Oude (Awadh) had been catalogued. Rehatsek, however, is not volunteering to compile said descriptive catalogue, for he is 62 years old and a liver complaint is his "inseparable companion for life". Included within the item are four leaves of manuscript revisions of the letter, possibly for publication.
- Arabic-Latin lexicon, ca. 1620?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8077416
  Extensive manuscript Arabic-Latin lexicon, very probably in the hand of Christoph Crinesus, inscribed on the front pastedown in a different hand from the manuscript itself, 'Opus M. Christoph Crinesii, Acad. Aldorff." The manuscipt on paper is arranged verso-recto with vellum tabs at fore-edge marking each letter of the Arabic alphabet; ruled in double columns (numbered to 539) and includes a Latin index, [29] leaves at end (11 leaves preceding the index and several pages elsewhere blank). The sources of the Arabic words and their meanings are recorded. These sources include 'Erp. Gram.' (i.e. Erpenius's Grammatica Arabica, first pulished in 1613), 'Proverb. Arab.' (i.e. Erpenius and Scaliger's Proverbiorum Arabicorum centuriae duae, 1614) and 'Matth.' (most likely Peter Kirsten's Notae in Evangelium S. Matthaei, 1611). There are also references to 'Tit.' (probably the Arabic edition of the Book of Titus published in Leiden in 1612), 'Judae" (an Arabic version of St. Jude's Epistle published in Breslau in 1611), and Kirsten's Grammatices Arabicae (1608).
- Chinese/English manuscript dictionary, 1818-1819
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8071777
  Original manuscript in ink, possibly the earliest substantial Chinese/English dictionary. The work consists of 1 p. captioned "Scale of Principal sounds in English & Chinese"; 3 pages with headings, but otherwise blank; 104 p. alphabetical index of English words or phrases with their equivalents in Chinese characters; 242 p., each divided into two vertical columns, with a listing of "13,316" characters with their meaning or meanings in English. Winthrop describes the work thus: "The foregoing is a translation of de Guignes great Chinese, french & Latin Dictionary, printed at Paris by order of Napoleon and finished in 1813. It was sent to me by an American Lady of my acquaintance who resides in Paris. I received it at Boston on 7 August, A.D. 1818 & about a week afterwards began this work, I finished it this 24th March A D 1818. Anno AEtatis 57. The original is a large folio of twelve hundred pages & printed on Vellulm paper. [signed] James Winthrop" -- final leaf.
- Terebi no naka ni wa nani mo nai, [20--?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/12426910
  Manuscript poem about "inside the TV"; title taken from first line.
- Ute Indian counting letter, 27 June 1925
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11344485
  Autographed letter, dated June 27, 1925 in Seattle, Washington, from Dr. James Branch Taylor to George W. Soliday about counting in the Ute language. Taylor joined Powell's 1828 expedition to Colorado, where he took notes on the Ute language; in this letter, he recounts "a fat old Indian, sitting astride a log ... recit[ing] to me the mode of counting" and lists Ute words for 1-33, 40-43, 50, 60, 70, 80, 90, and 100 next to the corresponding numbers with a few additional notes.
- Comparative vocabulary of the Algonkian dialects, 1893-1895
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8591115
  An original typed and handwritten manuscript, title page is dated 1893, which includes comparative lists arranged one word per page of over forty different Algonquin languages/dialects, apparently from both published and unpublished sources; the language names are typed, the words inserted by hand in ink. Pages 254-256 lists sources. With a letter from Wallace Tooker to Gatschet loosely inserted, dated October 16, 1895, discussing Algonquin terms for "rainbow."
- Woordenboek der neger-engelsche taal, 1846?
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8083550
  Manuscript copy of part of H.C. Kocke's Neger-Engelsch Woordenboek in two exercise books. Notes on the inside front covers identify the copyist as W. Boekhoudt "Gecopieerd in Maart 1846 door W. Boekhoudt." Volume 1 (p. 1-48 p.) includes A-H (harki). Volume 2 (p. 49-96) includes H (hárki) - N (nékki).
- The Man Who Watched the Trains Go By - filmscript, [195-?]
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8431539
  Mimeographed film script; numbered shots, camera and editing directions, dialogue, and action, with ms. annotations. "Please return to: Raymond Stross Productions LTD, 12 Bourdon Street, London ..." Printed label on p. [2] of wrappers: "Curtis and Page, 117 Finchley Road ... Typewriting--Duplicating." Film based on George Simenon's "Homme qui regardait passer les trains"; released in London 1952. In original plain red wrappers.
- Plays and Playgoers theatre diaries, 1913-1934
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8252964
  A collection of nine volumes of Plays and playgoers: a theatre-goer's record, which include first hand manuscript accounts of theater and musical productions, operas, and ballets performed in various venues primarily in Chicago and London from the years 1913 to 1934. The scrapbooks include playbills, newspaper, program and magazine clippings interspersed with detailed entries on each performance. The compiler of these scrapbooks is unknown.
- Thomas Dobson letter, 6 Nov. 1806
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8095094
  One page holograph letter signed, with integral address leaf, written at Philadelphia to the Editors of the Monthly anthology. Concerns the exchange of numbers of the Philadelphia medical museum, printed by Dobson, for numbers of the Monthly anthology.
- Words and Music - filmscript, 1948
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8248481
  Words and music (1948) is a movie loosely based on the lives and work of composer Richard Rodgers and lyricist Lorenz Hart.
- "Selected Poems and Songs" British commonplace book, [18--?]
  Gift: 2005
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8372379
  A British 19th century holograph commonplace book of selected poems and songs, with extracts and notes ([76] leaves of blue paper, watermarked 1797, bound in green cloth, printed label on spine). Selections include, for example, "The Vicar of Bray," William Cowper's Robinson Crusoe, "Nell Batchelor the Oxford Pye-Woman," and "The death of Nelson." Written on the front loose flyleaf: "Charles Baker's, If these selections were made & written by my Father, of which there is some evidence in the shapes of some of the capitals, they must have been executed before he adopted that fine Italian hand which he used for at least forty years ..." Baker appears to have practiced a variety of script styles.
- The Search for Hannah Swynock TMS, 1991
  Gift: 2014
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/13937016
  Photocopying permitted only with the permission of the Curator of Manuscripts, Lilly Library. A transcription by Jean Marr Wilkins (completed for a class assignment at Indiana University, Bloomington) of a 1687 commonplace book, believed to be written by an English woman, Hannah Swynock. The commonplace book is part of the Lilly Library's Parker manuscripts collection. "For Professor Solt's seminar, submitted by Jean Wilkins, 11 December 1991." Printed on one side only.
- Epigrams moral and entertaining - Cornelius Crowquill, 1821
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/11767906
  A manuscript volume of epigrams. The volume consists of two divisions: Epigrams moral and entertaining and A collection of amusing and instructive epigrams. Both divisions have their own title page and consist of 7 epigrams, each within a different decorative hand-drawn border.
- Rebus letter from Paterson, New Jersey, to a relative, 1 Apr. 1867
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/14382638
  Original rebus manuscript ([4] p.) with pen and ink, watercolor, and cutout images from printed sources; completed on both rectos and versos of two folio leaves. With approximately 800 words and 225 images. Pages have been re-tipped into original quarter leather folder with marbled boards. A family letter written as an April Fool's Day gift, from Paterson, NJ, where the unidentified author/artist had moved from New York in 1865. A business man and head of a family, he sends this to his aunt in New Bedford, both for amusement and for information on life in Paterson, where he works as a cashier and bookkeeper in the newly established Danforth (later Cooke) Locomotive and Machine Company. The letter also gives an interesting description of Paterson itself. The rebus is "signed" at the end with a cutout silhouette of the author. The autobiographical information and names of relatives cited in the letter might help to serve to identify the author.
- A collection of 10,180 proverbs, etc., [17--?]
  Gift: 2002
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/7202487
  Eighteenth-century manuscript of English, as well as biblical, proverbs and sayings. Tipped in at front is a note in the hand of Peter Opie that states that this is a collection "more of phrases & sayings than true proverbs. Compiled from various sources, but sources not given." Ms. note on front free endpaper notes that the "new endpapers with which the original MS is bound are dated 1847."
- Odelette guerrière, 1870
  See IUCAT record: https://iucat.iu.edu/catalog/8080499